Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's daf דף daf is ל"ח,
Lamed Chet, and we pick we were dealing with a whole discussion
about
a chazaka חזקה chazaka on trees and a chazaka חזקה chazaka on
the land that's around them and how that reflects certain realities of
somebody who sells trees and keeps for himself the land or sells
land and keeps for himself the trees or sells to two people,
one the trees and one the land, whether and in which cases
we're supposed to assume will there be some land that goes with
the trees or not, something that's actually discussed later in the Gemara
גמרא Gemara about two trees versus three trees and interestingly those issues
were not brought in here. But anyway the Gemara גמרא Gemara makes
a distinction between one set of considerations about mocher be'ayin yafa מוכר
בעין יפה, mocher be'ayin yafa, mocher be'ayin ra מוכר בעין רע, mocher
be'ayin ra, whether when one when there's one buyer and one seller,
whether we assume the seller means sort of very narrow terms or
more generous terms, and that's a different question when there are two
people that are buying the entire plot and there's a question how
did the seller intend to divide it between those two people. Okay
so that was one issue yesterday. And then the Gemara גמרא Gemara
transitioned to the discussion about an overcrowded plot of land where there
are too many trees and whether in that type of a case
a chazaka חזקה chazaka on the trees works on the land because
if it's seen that those trees are going to be uprooted, which
apparently everybody here understood told me was a standard in terms of
creating like nurseries and so on, you plant a lot in a,
the Rashbam רשב"ם Rashbam already says this, in a small in a
you know sort of a more condensed and then you uproot them
and replant them. So in that type of a case if it's
not seen as an ongoing relationship between the trees and the land
that they're planted in, so a chazaka חזקה chazaka on the trees
doesn't work with the land. Okay, so let's pick up now again
within that context, last line of ל"ז עמוד ב'. Lamed Zayin Amud
Bet. Amrei Nehardai אמרי נהרדאי, Amrei Nehardai, says Nehardai, hai man de'zavin
dikla le'chaverei האי מאן דזבין דיקלא לחבריה, hai man de'zavin dikla le'chaverei,
somebody who sells a palm tree to his friend, kanei lei mi-shippulei
tehoma קני ליה משיפולי תהומא, kanei lei mi-shippulei tehoma, takes possession of
the land underneath the tree from the sort of lip of the
surface all the way down to the depths. As I said I
don't know, as I said I don't know, as I said this
again is a question about how does this fit in with other
discussions about whether when you buy a tree you take land or
not. Anyway the Rashbam רשב"ם Rashbam says that maybe even if you
normally assume you don't normally assume you don't get the land we
normally do assume you don't get land with a tree, that's land
outside of the tree. But the land directly under the tree here
the argument is at least within the idea of mocher be'ayin yafa
מוכר בעין יפה mocher be'ayin yafa that you do get that land
directly underneath the tree. And now the point is not only do
you get the land directly underneath it but you get it going
all the way down. Okay so now the Gemara גמרא Gemara says,
matkif la Rava מתקיף לה רבא, Matkif la Rava, so Rava asked
on this, top of ל"ח עמוד א', Lamed Chet Amud Aleph, veleima
lei ולימא ליה veleima lei kurkema de'rishka zibni lach כורכמא דרישקא זבני
לך, kurkema de'rishka zibni lach, why can't the owner say to him
I sold you a saffron of rishka, a certain type of a
saffron. Saffron crocus, there you go. Isn't that standard saffron which is
saffron crocus?
I think it is.
Anyway, okay so that explains why kurkema כורכמא kurkema means saffron, crocus,
kurkema כורכמא kurkema I guess. Anyway so so why doesn't he say
that no it's like when you sell somebody a saffron plant that
the idea similar to what we said before is you own it
until it grows to a certain maturity and then you remove the
plant and it's not intended to be with the land underneath it.
So a kurkema de'rishka vezil כורכמא דרישקא וזיל, kurkema de'rishka vezil, uproot
it and leave. So apparently that was a type of a case
what was understood that you did not sell the underlying land and
here too is the same type of a question. Now again we
know obviously if you sold a tree you don't have to uproot
a tree, but the point being my whole point is to keep
the tree growing and keep the fruit, but the whole point being
but maybe once the tree dies you don't own the underlying land.
So it's going back to that same question, how do you know
whether you've sold the underlying land or not, or you just have
rights to it as long as the tree is around. So the
Gemara גמרא Gemara says, ela amar Rava אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar
Rava, so therefore Rava says, ba bemachmat ta'ana בבא במחמת טענה. ba
bemachmat ta'ana. So you're right, maybe when assuming we say that you
know when you buy one tree you don't buy the underlying land
which is again that discussion you know difference between one and two
trees as opposed to three. Maybe you don't even buy the land
directly under, all you do is you have rights to use that
land. But it doesn't mean it can't happen sometimes if it's set
explicitly. So let's say you actually say to the owner, no no
I know I didn't say you just stam סתם stam sold me
the tree. We agreed when you sold it to me that you
were selling me the underlying land. Okay that's a nice claim. But
if we assume in general that that's not what happens, how are
you going to be believed? Ah so now we finally get back
to chazaka חזקה. chazaka. Okay so I actually say, my claim is
you sold me the underlying land, that was explicit,
and I've been working the tree for three years and you never
said anything and that proves that I own the underlying land. The
only problem is how does that prove anything? If your normal ownership
of a single tree is without the underlying land, how is this
a meaningful chazaka חזקה? chazaka? So let's take a look. Amar lei
Mar Keshisha berei de אמר ליה מר קשישא בריה ד Amar lei
Mar Keshisha berei de אמר ליה מר קשישא בריה דרב חסדא לרב
אשי Amar lei Mar Kashisha brei de'Rav Chisda l'Rav Ashi האי קורקמא
דרישכא זביני ליה hai kurkema d'rishka zavni lei מה הוה ליה למימר?
mah havay lei l'meimar? So one minute, but if he did sell
him the saffron or by analogy, if he did sell him a
tree only to be there temporarily or to be there as long
as the tree was going but not with the underlying land, what
should the owner then do? How should the original owner you know
protect himself against a claim that this guy actually he'll claim he
bought the underlying land and he'll say he has a חזקה? chazakah?
So how do you protect yourself against that claim? So the Gemara
says: איבעי ליה למחויי. ibayei lei limchu'ei. You have to make a
מחאה. mecha. So look, this is very parallel not only is it
is it is it analogous actually the Gemara is going to quote
the exact same discussion of the Gemara earlier about the fact that
people can be on land for three years having nothing to do
with ownership, sharecropping, rental. So how are you supposed to protect yourself?
Because there's other ways of explaining what the person is doing there.
And the point is, if you want to protect yourself, you have
to make a מחאה. mecha. And the מחאה, mecha, the חידוש chiddush
is that a מחאה mecha is not just you're stealing my land,
a מחאה mecha is even like you make a declaration, I want
everybody to know that פלוני Ploni is on my land because he's
a sharecropper. פלוני Ploni is harvesting the tree but I only sold
him the tree, I didn't sell him the underlying land. Okay.
How would you translate the exact term? Because doesn't it have the
sense of also like not just clarifying but sort of protest?
Yeah, it's a protest. So that's why, but in this context you're
not protesting that somebody is doing something wrong. You are making an
official statement, yeah, you're registering a statement. I know and that's why
it's a strange idea because as you know David correctly pointed out
the other day, the
it's not so clear that that people are going to care about
that like that's not good gossip. Oh, did you hear that so-and-so
said that this guy was a sharecropper? Well, let's talk about that!
You know. Oh, did you hear he said he only owned the
tree, he didn't own the land? Like nobody's going to talk about
it so how is he supposed to figure that this guy is
going to find out and going to protect his שטר, shtar, right?
So, you know, at least if there was some central registry where
you could file papers, right, and you're filing a motion or papers
that you're planning you're protecting your claim and if I want to
if I'm the if I'm the guy that's on it I can
go check and see if you filed those papers or not, right,
that makes sense, but it's hard so it's a complicated system, right?
People have what?
That's how they do it today.
With some with some yeah decentralized yeah centralized system, right. Okay, so
anyway but that's the point, there are reasons why somebody's on it
having nothing to do with ownership. Maybe you just bought the tree,
you didn't buy the underlying land or it wouldn't be the default,
maybe you're just a sharecropper, maybe you're whatever. So what do you
have to do to prevent the guy from making a claim that
he owns it? You have to go ahead and make it offi
and and do a מחאה mecha and for some reason that מחאה
mecha works. איבעי ליה למחויי. ibayei lei limchu'ei. די לאו תימא הכי,
di lav teima hachi, if you don't say that, הני משכנתא דסורא,
hani mashkanta d'Sura, here we go, exact Gemara as we had before,
במישכנתא דסורא b'mashkanta d'Sura דכתיב ביה d'chtiv beih
basically, you know, you you lent somebody ten thousand dollars, you sit
on their land and you harvest the fruit for a period of
time and after you've harvested the fruit for ten years or whatever
it is, then your debt is paid the debt is paid off.
And it's written in the משכנתא, mashkanta, במישלם שניא אילו b'mishlam shnaya
ilu
at the end of this period of time, these ten years or
whatever the amount might be, תיפוק ארעא בלא כספא. tipok ara belo
chaspa. This land goes back to the original owner and the debt
is paid off. Okay, so somebody will be on ראובן Reuven will
be on שמעון's Shimon land not because he owns it, but he'll
be on it for ten years harvesting all of the fruit and
that might be why the Gemara gives this as an example as
opposed to a sharecropper because a sharecropper maybe you'll see that the
guy gives some of the fruit back to the original owner, right,
but here the guy is harvesting all of the produce for himself
and what is what's going to stop him from claiming it's his?
Okay. אי כבשי ליה לשטר משכנתא i kavshi lei l'shtar mashkanta if
the person who has the debt who's the one, you know, the
creditor who's the one that has the IOU, has the documentation. If
he were to hide it at the end of ten years ואמר
לקוחה היא בידי v'amar lekuha hi beyadi this actually is my is
my field I purchased it, הכא נמי דמהימן hacha nami d'meheiman would
he be believed? מתקני רבנן מילתא דאתי בה לידי פסידא matkni rabanan
milta d'ati bah lidei pseida would the rabbis establish something that could
lead to a loss? אלא איבעי ליה למחויי. ela ibayei lei limchu'ei.
It must be that the original owner can make a מחאה. mecha.
That's what he can do to protect himself and that type of
a מחאה mecha works even though it's not a מחאה mecha as
kind of a protest this guy's a גזלן, gazlan, everybody is doing
everything legally and on the up and up, but you make an
official declaration, I'm declaring in front of you that this is the
context in which the person is on the land and if you
do that ahead of three years that's going to work. הכא נמי
איבעי ליה למחויי. hacha nami ibayei lei limchu'ei. So here too, if
you buy the tree without the underlying land and you don't want
him to claim that he has the underlying land, you make the
מחאה. mecha. So you could by the way realize, you know, that
this also is given to a lot of abuse in the other
way, right, because here what I'm going to do is I'm going
to go ahead and sell you this land and then I'll make
a מחאה mecha that says that hey guys you should know that
Eli's on my land it's a משכנתא mashkanta I never sold it
to him, okay, or you know Eli's on it so and if
again assuming that the word won't get to him as well as
if I say he's a גזלן, gazlan, right, or I might play
the odds, maybe it will maybe it won't but like what do
I have
I have a relatively good good chance of the fact that he
won't have held on to his שטר, shtar, so you know, it's
it's if this מחאה mechah is not going to be as talked
about and the and the word won't get to the other person,
it's also given to abuse so people are still going to have
to be pretty careful holding onto their שטרות, shtarot, like this is
not a full proof system. Yes.
Relate what you're saying. You know what bothers me is the wording
of כובש לשטריה. Kovish leishtei. I would have wanted to say destroyed
the שטר. shtar. Like what is there any import to that? It's
a funny term. Yeah. Like why would he hold onto it if
he wanted to make that claim? Right. It could be
rediscovered
afterwards. Does that answer your question?
Yeah, yeah, no I understand that.
Wording aside, I mean,
conceptually it means to suppress. There are different ways of suppressing. Why
would he hold onto it? Yeah, I don't know. I don't know
why you'd hold onto it. Because the smart thing is to do,
you never know when you're going to need that... you might lose
your claim and you're going to need that documentation. The smart thing
is to hide it, not to destroy it. But I don't know.
Yes.
Is it seem strange that what you need is עדים eidim that
you made the declaration as opposed to עדים eidim to the original
transaction that support the
declaration?
If I can just strengthen that? I mean at the end of
the day all the עדים eidim are testifying to is that you
said something.
Right. Not that it was true.
Right.
Right. So, yeah, but I guess it's a question about the... so
you're saying but let's just test that in terms of a normal
חזקה. chazakah. I sell my... somebody is on my land. Oh you're
saying like this. In a normal חזקה chazakah where somebody is adverse
possession, there is no original transaction. So the only thing that's available
to me as the original owner is to make a מחאה. mechah.
Whereas in a case where there was an original transaction,
then what's available to me as the owner is to actually say
look here's the witnesses and here were the terms of the agreement.
Hmm.
Wait, why aren't the terms of agreement like a fact?
Well they are, but who's to prove it? How do you prove
that? That's the question. So the point is that in a normal
case, in a normal חזקה, chazakah, either he's a גזלן gazlan and
therefore there are no witnesses and all I have available to me
is a מחאה. mechah. But in this case, why don't I actually...
so let's think. So if I... if I'm on Eli's land here
as a משכון, mashkon, why isn't it Eli's responsibility to hold onto...
why does he have the option of making a מחאה, mechah, why
isn't it his responsibility to make sure that he has documentation or
he has עדים eidim to it?
Right. The מחאה mechah doesn't include עדים? eidim?
It does, but it's עדים eidim of מחאה, mechah, it's not עדים
eidim of direct testimony of the facts of the case.
So if I go ahead and the עדים eidim just say I
made a מחאה. mechah. So if I go ahead and I sell...
or I sell this tree and I'm afraid that David is going
to claim that he owns the land, why in order to protect
myself don't I have to maintain proof about the nature of the
transaction or have עדים eidim of the nature of the transaction? It's
a good question, especially in this context where it's given for my
abuse because because it's a type of
a מחאה mechah that doesn't necessarily reach the person on the land
with the same force and it's a case where there actually is
an original transaction that you could have evidence of or you could
ensure to have evidence of. It's a very good question. Yeah, I
don't know. I don't know.
Yeah, you know if you understand that שני לוחות shnei luchot as
being two copies as opposed to and the two copies of because
there are obligations in both directions.
Who says so? What? That's a nice פשט. pshat. What?
Okay yeah. I don't know I thought that. Anyway, so but the
point is that
shouldn't you know shouldn't within, right
it could be two copies of a, right two copies of a
contract
where there are obligations,
right exactly exactly yeah I said that before which is is that
the funny thing is you know you imagine in a type of
a שותפות shutafut there will be two copies of the contract, but
in these types of transactions where you there's generally assumed to be
one person who's like you know who's, you know that one person
primarily needs the evidence against the other person, we generally assume one
copy. But I completely agree. Like a lot of this will be
solved if there's if there's two copies of the contract. But the
general question about when there is an original transaction and when therefore
he's there legitimately and the מחאה mechah won't get there as well,
why not obligate there to be direct evidence about that? That's a
very good question. Eli what were you...
I was just going to all the cases we saw it's been
down to two contracts...
right I know I know we never hear of two contracts, right?
We always assume that there's fundamentally one שטר. shtar. There's one person
who's going to collect... exactly. And you know and that's a funny
question, like הלכה halachah why don't we find that more exactly for
a case like this? But that's a and just one more sentence
of thought about this and then we'll move. Does it make sense,
like there's also the question of like to whom to put the
burden on, right? Does it make more sense, like if we were
to say that, you know, if we if Eli let if I
lent Eli money and I'm on the land and I'm the משכונא
mashkona or whatever for him to protect himself, he should get witnesses.
Does it make is is there something unfair about does that create
too much of an undue burden on him?
Like witnesses that they witnessed the two of you together.
Yeah, they witness the nature of the original transaction, right. I'm not
sure that that makes sense in terms of what do you call
it, in terms of like okay, that puts greater that puts a
greater burden on the person with the original land, but I don't
understand why it's necessarily makes more sense to create like any more
burden on you is less burden on me and vice versa. Yeah,
so I don't know. It's a really good question why this works.
המוציא מחבירו Hamotzi mechavero even though that...
Well, that's always going to be the question. That's what I'm saying.
The question about whether you suffice with a מחאה mecha'ah or whether
you need a whether you need direct witnesses is a question of
the degree of burden you put on a particular person, okay, but
why we should דוקא davka assume we should want to lighten the
burden on one side rather than the other?
Well, because listen, because fundamentally it was always my stuff. So why
should I go out of my way to like, you know, to
You're the one who wants to prove that that
Yeah, but there's all cases given to abuse, you know? So there's
a general question about what you know what's going to be the
best in terms of the society. I think it's a very good
question.
I mean I never sold you land what I'm saying, right? That's
the thing with the מחאה, mecha'ah, you're the one who wants to
take the land away from me. Why am I going out of
my way to make it easier for you? All I have to
do is just do a מחאה. mecha'ah. But what if you did
sell?
What if you did Right.
Yeah, it's it's a real good question why מחאה mecha'ah works in
this case, especially and I really do appreciate the sharpening of it
that it's that there is actually a legitimate transaction that there could
be evidence of. All right, let's take a look now at the
next משנה. Mishna. Okay. שלש ארצות לחזקה. Shalosh aratzot lachazakah. יהודה ועבר
הירדן והגליל. Yehuda ve'ever haYarden vehaGalil.
Now we're dealing with this exact issue of the מחאה mecha'ah getting
from one person to another. So we have to say now you
could also say it's about the news of the חזקה chazakah getting
from one person to the other. So we have to assume that
news is going to travel. So news travels within a country, it
doesn't travel from country to country, at least as a general rule
we'll see about this in the גמרא. Gemara.
So there are It's important exactly. So exactly, exactly, and for שביעית
Shevi'it etc. So it's important to identify that there's three different basic
locales in which you know sort of there's a lot of travel
and and news you know sort of moves around within one country
but not necessarily between country and country or region. Okay, so there's
the Judea, Transjordan, and the Galilee.
יהודה Yehuda yes, יהודה Yehuda all of Southern Israel? Is that or
is that?
Yeah, I think so. I mean I assume the places that was
at the time of the משנה Mishna that was you know had
Jewish settlements. I don't know the you know I'd have to It's
a good question. I mean there's a משנה Mishna in שביעית Shevi'it
if I remember correctly that lays out the exact parameters of the
what do you have...
Yeah, the Galilee goes all the way as far south as what
we'd call שומרון. Shomron. Yeah, that's north of Jerusalem. יהודה Yehuda starts
south of Jerusalem. Right. It's discussed in שביעית. Shevi'it.
Right.
היה ביהודה והחזיק בגליל, בגליל והחזיק ביהודה. Haya vihuda vehechezik baGalil, baGalil
vehechezik biYehuda. So if you the original owner was in one place
and the person taking possession of your land was in the other
region, אינה חזקה. eina chazakah. It's not a חזקה. chazakah. עד שיהא
עמו במדינה אחת, Ad sheyehe imo bemedina achat, until you're in the
same area because presumably if the חזקה chazakah works that says like
you know if you if I didn't legitimately own it and you
should you the original owner should have protested then your first claim
is well how was I supposed to know you were there? Okay,
so you have to be a place where you assume the news
will get. Now the second part also will be that now we
also have to assume that if you do protest that information could
have got to me. Okay, we'll get about to that in the
גמרא. Gemara. But there has to be So therefore חזקה chazakah will
not work if they're in different places where you don't assume the
news will travel.
Generally people call this, you have to keep your שטר shtar in
many cases a long time.
That is true. אמר רב יהודה. Amar Rav Yehuda. So said רב
יהודה. Rav Yehuda. לא אמרו שלש ארצות אלא כדי שיהא באספמיא ויחזיק
שנה, וילכו ויודיעוהו שנה, ויבא שנה אחרת. Lo amru shalosh aratzot ela
kedei sheyehe be'Aspamya veyachazik shana, veyeilchu veyodi'uhu shana, veyavo shana acheret. So
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says that actually no, there is no boundaries.
Your חזקה chazakah can work from if you're if you're halfway across
the world, okay, Spain, that would be the example of being halfway
across the world, and the ראשונים Rishonim say it really doesn't matter
even if you're further, but Spain was the assumption that that would
be...
אספמיא Aspamya means Spain? Yeah, that that's not a place in Spain,
it actually means Spain?
No, I think Spain. Okay. So anyway so that would be even
if you were in a very far away place, the assumption would
be that you would get could get the message within a year,
that you would protest and the message would get back within a
year. Might take a year for the person
adverse possession to actually, you know, register for people and them to
start talking about it and so on, okay, but ultimately once that
once people started talking about it you would get the message within
a year and you'd be able to get a message back within
a year. Okay, so that's רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda claim and therefore
the ראשונים Rishonim say that even if he's in a place that's
further than a year away it's like לא פלוג, lo plug, but
the basic point is that they gave three years to say that
a חזקה chazakah will work. If he's in front of him?
Okay, so right of course one question to ask would be would
be that if it was directly in the person's presence maybe חזקה
chazakah should work immediately. Exactly, and the גמרא Gemara and so we
will see that. The other question here also is that it says
ויבא לשנה אחרת. Veyavo leshana acheres. You have to return in the
next year to protest, which makes it sound like and the גמרא's
Gemara's going to say that according to רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, מחאה
mecha'ah has to be בפניו. befanav. If you're מוחה שלא בפניו, mocheh
shelo befanav, if you're מוחה mocheh in Spain and the message gets
back to the guy, that might not be enough. You have to
return personally. On the one hand, what? An agent can't? It's an
interesting question. If there's a difference, you're right, there's a difference between
me coming personally, סתם stam people talking about it, and me sending
somebody to represent me, a שליח. shaliach. Okay, right, that's so that's
a good question. But so we'll take, we'll see about that.
But the basic point is that on the one hand he gives
a lot of, well, on the one hand actually I realized that
they reinforce. He actually his two פסקים psakim jointly very much favors
the מחזיק. machzik. Because number one, they allow the מחזיק machzik to
hold on to it even if the original owner is very far
away. And number two, they allow the מחזיק machzik to hold on
to it unless the original owner came and does a personal protest.
So his two פסקים psakim very much favor the מחזיק machzik and
put a heavy demand on the original owner that he finds out
even if he's far away, we're assuming he's going to find out
or he has a responsibility to find out and if he knows
he has a responsibility to come back in person. So that's רבי
יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. Why it requires an initial year for him for
people to start talking about it, you know, that's also an interesting
question, but and also the one that Michael asked, which is what
if it's directly in his presence? Does the חזקה chazakah work automatically
or after a year? Good questions. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says מאי קסבר תנא קמא?
Mai kasavar Tanna Kamma? What does the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma of
the opinion of? אי קסבר מחאה שלא בפניו הויא מחאה, Ei kasavar
mecha'ah shelo befanav havya mecha'ah, so אפילו יהודה וגליל נמי. afillu Yehuda
veGalil nami. If he holds that a מחאה mecha'ah not in the
person's presence works, so why so then it should be able to
work from different countries? Which is like obviously. Obviously the whole point
is that you need it to be considered to be like you
know within a you know more close, in a region that you
can that you can hear.
So... אי קסבר מחאה שלא בפניו הויא מחאה, Ei kasavar mecha'ah shelo
befanav havya mecha'ah, if you could be מוחה mocheh at a distance,
so אפילו יהודה וגליל נמי, afillu Yehuda veGalil nami, so then a
חזקה chazakah should work even between יהודה Yehuda and גליל. Galil. Now
why does it say מחאה? mecha'ah? Why doesn't it say חזקה שלא
בפניו? chazakah shelo befanav? Okay, so let's pause for a moment about
this. So
the basic explanation of why it doesn't say חזקה chazakah is because
the meaning of חזקה chazakah derives from the absence of מחאה. mecha'ah.
So therefore, in order to say that my חזקה chazakah is meaningful,
why is my being here meaningful for three years? Well, it's not
that being here is meaningful, it's being here with you not reacting
is what shows that I own it. Okay, so if we want
to say, does my חזקה chazakah work at a distance, what we're
going to say is does the absence of your מחאה mecha'ah work
at a distance? Because consider, let's say we were to say that
when you would be מוחה mocheh at a distance it would not
work because we would assume that the message would not get to
me. So should therefore should my חזקה chazakah work at a distance?
Well if the only reason my חזקה chazakah works is because we're
trying to prove something from the absence of your מחאה. mecha'ah. But
you wouldn't be bothered being מוחה mocheh anyway because the message wasn't
going to get to me anyway. So the absence of your מחאה
mecha'ah doesn't mean anything. So because the absence of מחאה, mecha'ah, because
מחאה שלא בפניו, mecha'ah shelo befanav, if we say מחאה שלא בפניו
mecha'ah shelo befanav doesn't work, it means because we assume it won't
get to me. Okay? So if we assume that מחאה שלא בפניו
mecha'ah shelo befanav won't get to me, then therefore my חזקה chazakah
doesn't mean anything, because then the absence of a מחאה mecha'ah is
meaningless. Now that's all very nice, but it's a little
roundabout. Still, why don't we just say the reason חזקה שלא בפניו
chazakah shelo befanav doesn't work is because the message won't get to
you, not because your מחאה mecha'ah won't get to me. Let's start
at the first stage, right? Of course it's not meaningful, of course
the person wasn't מוחה mocheh because he didn't even find out about
it. So תוספות Tosafot says, תוספות Tosafot makes a very good point,
which is that we have to assume this gets back to the
rumor mill and people talking like the discussion before, you know, it's
a better gossip item that I am adversely possessing Eli's land than
it is that Eli is making a protest. I mean maybe if
Eli's protest is דוב הוא גזלן, Dov hu gazlan, then that gets
people talking, which we're going to see is the classic protest. Okay,
but the first thing that's the real so A: it's a juicier
piece of gossip that I'm on his land. B: not only is
it a juicier piece of gossip, but people are going to be
more interested in telling Eli that fact. Eli, did you know that
דוב Dov is on your land and he's taking possession of it?
Did you sell it to him? So there's greater assumption that that
message of the adverse possession is going to get to Eli than
there is that when Eli says דוב הוא גזלן, Dov hu gazlan,
that the message is going to get back to me. That's תוספות'ס
Tosafot's assertion. Okay, so therefore or you know A: I'm just sort
of saying it in the way in which people gossip, but people
could also say... תוספות Tosfos I think also adds about whether, you
know, the original, is the other side looking for that information? If
I have gone to Spain or wherever I've gone, I've gone out
of my town, and I've left some plots of lands behind, I'm
going to be asked or אלי, Eli, let's keep אלי's Eli original
owner, אלי's Eli going to be asking people, "Is anything—how are my
fields doing? Is anything up with my fields? Anything I should know
about my fields?" Okay, because he's left them and therefore he's going
to be eager to hear that information. So he's going to get
the information of my adverse possession, you know, more likely. Whereas if
I
legitimately owned the land and bought it from אלי, Eli, okay, and
he's in some other town, it's less likely that I'm going to
be regularly checking in to find out, "Hey, do you know if
אלי's Eli registered a false claim about the fact that I bought
his land?" Okay? So, right, so תוספות Tosfos makes a very good
point that it is more likely the חזקה Chazakah message gets to
the original owner than that the מחאה Mecha'ah message gets to the
person. So therefore תוספות Tosfos says, we don't have a problem with
חזקה שלא בפניו. Chazakah she-lo befanav. We can take it for granted
that if I'm in יהודה Yehuda and אלי's Eli in גליל Galil
that אלי's Eli going to find out. That's not a question. Everybody
can assume that. Okay, חזקה שלא בפניו, Chazakah she-lo befanav, the message
is going to get to the person. The question is, will the
מחאה Mecha'ah get back to the guy who's מחזיק? Machzik? And that's
the issue because מחאה Mecha'ah doesn't travel as, you know, as widely
and as strongly as the as the message of the חזקה. Chazakah.
So therefore we say, if מחאה שלא בפניו Mecha'ah she-lo befanav isn't
going to work, if אלי's Eli מחאה Mecha'ah won't get back to
me, okay, then then he's not going to bother to be מוחה
Mocheh and whatever, and then the meaning—there's no meaning to my חזקה
Chazakah because there's no absence of מחאה Mecha'ah that's meaningful. If מחאה
שלא בפניו Mecha'ah she-lo befanav will work, then he should be מוחה
Mocheh and the absence of מחאה Mecha'ah is meaningful. Okay, so what
this explains is that whether מחאה Mecha'ah works שלא בפניו she-lo befanav
determines if חזקה Chazakah works, but the reason to focus on מחאה,
Mecha'ah, says תוספות, Tosfos, is because we can assume that the חזקה
Chazakah will spread. The חזקה Chazakah message will get to the person,
but what we can't assume is that the מחאה Mecha'ah will get
back to—will get back. Okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara wants
to say. מאי קסבר? Mai Kasavar? אי קסבר Ei Kasavar מחאה שלא
בפניו הויא מחאה, Mecha'ah she-lo befanav havya Mecha'ah, if he's of the
opinion that the מחאה Mecha'ah in a distance will work, so אפילו
יהודה וגליל נמי afillu Yehuda ve-Galil nami then my חזקה Chazakah should
work, because I should hear the מחאה Mecha'ah and since I didn't,
and he should have been מוחה Mocheh and since he didn't, it
proves that I own it.
ואי קסבר Ve-ei Kasavar מחאה שלא בפניו לא הויא מחאה, Mecha'ah she-lo
befanav lo havya Mecha'ah, but if the מחאה Mecha'ah at a distance
won't get back to the guy who's מחזיק, Machzik, אפילו יהודה
ויהודה נמי לא. afillu Yehuda vi-Yehuda nami lo. So then even if
he's just out of the same town, even in the same country,
if it's not directly in my presence, maybe I could always claim,
"Oh, you know, I didn't know, I was ignorant, you said you
were מוחה, Mocheh, maybe you were, I never got that message" and
so on, so then it shouldn't work even in the same country,
you should demand it to be בפניו. befanav. So the גמרא Gemara
says, so נמי לא. nami lo. אמר אבא בר ממל אמר רב
Amar Abba bar Mammel amar Rav לעולם קסבר מחאה שלא בפניו הויא
מחאה. l'olam kasavar Mecha'ah she-lo befanav havya Mecha'ah. You don't have to
directly show up and say it in the person's face. Okay, that's
the בפניו. befanav. Right, there's three stages. There's saying it to the
person's face, that's בפניו. befanav. Then there's שלא בפניו she-lo befanav in
the same country, where the message will get to him or you
can assume it'll get to him, but you didn't say it to
his face. And then there is מחאה שלא בפניו Mecha'ah she-lo befanav
in a different country. So מחאה בפניו Mecha'ah befanav we don't need.
You don't need to say—רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says the guy's got to return from Spain. But we don't
need that. We don't need you to say it to the person's
face. Okay, הויא מחאה. havya Mecha'ah. משנתנו בשעת חירום שנו. Mishnatenu be-sha'at
herum shanu. But so that's true, that's why יהודה ויהודה Yehuda vi-Yehuda
work, because you assume the message gets to him. But יהודה וגליל
Yehuda ve-Galil doesn't work, because there, that's worse than שלא בפניו. she-lo
befanav. There, it's like חירום herum is like that there's this enmity
between the two regions, and we assume that there's not a lot
of travel, there's a travel ban on, okay, so therefore, everybody's being
stopped at the airport and therefore no message is getting, no message
is getting
to the other side. And because no message is getting to the
other side, it's not just שלא בפניו, she-lo befanav, it's that the
message just doesn't even get there.
שעת חירום Sha'at herum here doesn't mean a temporary sort of crisis
type of situation, it means the
general—yeah, the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it is that there's general
animosity between the two regions.
So it's a normal state of affairs.
Yeah, right, שעת חירום Sha'at herum sounds like it's temporary, but it
doesn't matter if it's temporary or if it's ongoing. Okay, it just
means that there is a, you know, there's antagonism there and therefore
we cannot assume—we cannot assume a high degree of travel, right. ומאי
שנא יהודה וגליל דנקט? U-mai shena Yehuda ve-Galil denakat? So why mention
יהודה וגליל? Yehuda ve-Galil? קמ"ל Kamashma lan it tells us that סתם
יהודה וגליל כשעת חירום דמו, stam Yehuda ve-Galil k'sha'at herum damu, that
we should generally assume that יהודה וגליל Yehuda ve-Galil
are—now it doesn't necessarily mean that are they really antagonistic or does
it just mean that there can be situations that are analogous to
an antagonistic region? Maybe there's just other regions, countries, you know, don't
do a lot of travel. Nobody in יהודה Yehuda is interested in
גליל, Galil, גליל Galil is interested in יהודה, Yehuda, like you know,
I mean, you know, US and Canada, there's no antagonism, but is
there
a lot
of... shorter distances between the US and Canada. So it's not necessarily
antagonism, there's just that there's just what?
Just Montreal has great kosher food.
I'm sure it does. Anyway, so יהודה גליל. Yehuda Galil. All right,
moving on.
Moving on, okay? So whether it's because of antagonism and whether it's
because of just other reasons, if there is a lot if there
doesn't tend to be serious traffic between the two, you can't assume
that the message gets there. All right, so there's three states. שלא
בפניו shelo befanav works. You don't have to show up and say
to the person's face. Now by the way, what would be the
reason of to require בפניו? befanav? The reason to require בפניו befanav
could be two reasons. Number one is can I assume, and this
is what the גמרא Gemara is going to shift to, that if
I say something not directly in his presence the message will get
to him. Maybe it will never get to him. But the other
point is that even if there's a good likelihood it'll get to
him, he could always claim it didn't get to him. Right, and
think about that gets back to some of the issues before. Like
I'm going to say, you know, Eli, you should have known about
it. You should have held about your שטר. shtar. I was מוחה.
moche. He says I never heard about it. What do you mean?
I told people, they're going to gossip.
They didn't gossip. I didn't hear about it, right? So is that
fair to Eli to say where's your שטר shtar because you definitely
heard about it? What do you mean definitely? Like, okay, likely that
he heard about it, but it's quite possible he didn't. So if
you require בפניו, befanav, right, then you are basically sort of saying
like, oh, so then I'm going to go בפניו befanav and I'm
going to go with the witnesses בפניו, befanav, there'll be no questions
about the fact that he got the information. Okay, so the reason
to require בפניו befanav is not just that it will make sure
he got it, but that there will be evidence that he got
it. Meaning I could say שלא בפניו shelo befanav I'm willing to
do that because it's because we'll presume he'll get it, but that
assumes two things. It assumes number one there's a good likelihood he'll
get it, and that, you know, that you'll be okay even though
you can't prove that. And that'll be actually to his detriment.
So בפניו befanav literally means in front of his face or does
it mean like the same neighborhood?
No, no, no, בפניו befanav means in front of his face.
Yes. What if there is traffic back and forth, meaning does it
have to be like the Canada example, something like that? Because like
there's people who go on business to Canada all the time. There's
not so many tourists, but like in this case does it have
to be someone who's likely to talk to Eli?
So we're going to get to that a little bit. I mean
the גמרא Gemara discussed earlier the question about people that are busy
with their business and are they therefore going to bother to be
מוחה? moche? So we're going to discuss a little bit like the
nature of the people that are gossiping, not exactly in that context,
but yeah. Okay, so בפניו befanav you understand why you need that,
okay, why you would want to demand that. A, it would clearly
put Eli on notice, and B, there would not be a question
about the facts. שלא בפניו shelo befanav means assuming number one that
we can assume that it's a good likelihood he'll get it, but
B, it also means that he's going to be in, like even
if he didn't get it, tough luck on him, okay, and that's
a little bit feels a little unfair, okay.
And that's the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma perspective. שלא בפניו shelo befanav
is also okay.
תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma,
that's exactly what we're saying. So שלא בפניו shelo befanav is okay
means we're going to assume he's going to get it, and whether
he did or he didn't because we're assuming he did, tough luck
on him if he didn't. So therefore שלא בפניו shelo befanav works,
but only in the same country or only in regions where there's
a lot of travel where we'll assume that he will get the
information.
Yes. What about an agent? In other words, if I was...
Yeah, you asked about the agent.
No, no, but if I was planning to go abroad and I
had property, I would probably appoint somebody to oversee my property. So
can that agent on his own...
Oh, that's a nice idea. To take the initiative...
Oh, that's a good point.
That's a good point. I mean I assume if you officially represent...
That's a very good point. Can somebody, if he has an official
capacity like an אפוטרופוס apotropus and so on, but if he's somebody
that his only job is to be מוחה, moche, he doesn't have
any autonomy with the property itself, his only job is to be
מוחה, moche, then it probably doesn't work, but it's a good question.
Like why wouldn't you say that
I can have witnesses that I made somebody whatever...
Well, you can do something to benefit somebody even if they're not
in front of you, right? So זכין. zachin.
Yeah, but no, but it gets to be a whole problem. No,
no, but even if you did appoint them. But it gets to
be a whole problem about... it gets to be a whole problem
about protecting the interests of the other party. Because here's what I'm
going to do, David. I'm going to sell you my plot of
land in secret. I am going to go ahead and appoint Michael,
my agent. I'll have two witnesses, but you don't know about it,
to be my agent to be מוחה. moche. I'm going to leave,
Michael's going to be מוחה moche and say you're eating... you're on
Dov's property illegitimately, and you're going to laugh it off because who
the heck is Michael to be making that claim? And I didn't
make that claim. So there's always this question about right trying... you
know, anytime you... like there's always tradeoffs in terms of whose interests
are you protecting. So but I understand the question. But I assume
therefore... I don't know, I'm just guessing that if Michael... actually has
some autonomy with my property, right, and therefore, you know, that then
he's not just some stranger saying, but I don't know, it's a
good, it's a really, it's a good question. Let's get further in
the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar
Rav, says רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of רב. Rav.
אין מחזיקין בנכסי בורח. Ein machzikin benichsei boreach.
You cannot go ahead and do a חזקה chazaka on somebody's property
if somebody is running away. Somebody is running away because the government
is after him, we'll find out that the government could be after
him for one of two reasons: either because he owes them money,
or, right, or because, right, either because we'll see, like, claim murder
or some type of a thing that they're going to, some real
type of corporal punishment that they want to do to him. So,
he's running away. And I figure, okay, you know, Dov had to
leave town, they're going to, no, not Dov. Michael, Michael had to
leave town because he is running away. He's in Spain where there's
no extradition treaty, or maybe there is, I don't know, and while
he's there, I'm going to be מחזיק machzik in his קרקע. karka.
Perfect! So, is it going to work? Now, even if we say
it works שלא בפניו. shelo befanav. Now, I gave an example of
Spain, I gave an example of Spain where it's a different country,
so let's not do that. Anyway, he left, he's hiding out in,
he's hiding out in Florida, okay? He's hiding out in Florida, we're
all in the United States, he can get the message, he can
get it back to me. So maybe it could work, because even
though he's hiding out, right, maybe he can still hear about what's
happening and be protest. The question, of course, will be if he
protest, would you,
if he protest, if he protest, is he going to give away
his location? Okay, so that's obviously a reason that maybe if he's
not able to protest because he'll give away his location, the חזקה
chazaka won't be meaningful. But initially, the גמרא Gemara understands that we're
not concerned about him giving away his location,
that where that the government is not going to chase him down
to Florida, the New York government, even though it knows where he
is. So for right now, we're going to assume that בורח boreach
is just a case of not being around, but not a case
of not being, about being afraid to reveal your location. Let's read
a little bit more. אמר רב אין מחזיקין בנכסי בורח. Amar Rav
ein machzikin benichsei boreach. A חזקה chazaka won't work. כי אמריתה קמי
דשמואל, Ki amritah kamei deShmuel, when I said it in front of
שמואל, Shmuel, אמר לי, amar li, וכי למחוות בפניו הוא צריך? vechi
limchot befanav hu tzarich?
Why doesn't it work? Do you think that the original owner has
to go and show up and directly in his presence? השתא מחאה
שלא בפניו Hashta mecha'ah shelo befanav works. So since
מחאה שלא בפניו mecha'ah shelo befanav works, he doesn't see בורח boreach
as different than anybody who's not around, so why should it be
a problem? ורב מאי קמשמע לן? veRav mai kamashma lan? So then
what is רב Rav trying to tell us when he says it
doesn't work? מחאה שלא בפניו לא הויה מחאה. mecha'ah shelo befanav lo
havya mecha'ah. Presumably, רב Rav is saying rather than seeing בורח boreach
as an unusual case, it's basically saying that just a מחאה mecha'ah
not in the presence doesn't work. ואמר רב מחאה שלא בפניו הויה
מחאה, Ve'amar Rav mecha'ah shelo befanav havya mecha'ah, but didn't רב Rav
explain the משנה Mishnah that the reason it works יהודה ביהודה Yehuda
biYehuda is because you don't have to be in somebody's presence? So
here too why should that be any different? So the גמרא Gemara
says, רב טעמא דתנא דידן קמפרש וליה לא סבירא ליה. Rav ta'ama
detana didan kamefaresh vlei lo sevira lei. No, רב Rav was explaining
the תנא קמא's Tanna Kamma's position, it works יהודה ביהודה Yehuda biYehuda
in two different places, but he actually holds like רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. He holds that you have to actually be in the guy's
presence, and therefore, and therefore בורח boreach doesn't work. Of course, it's
very strange, why give an extreme case of בורח boreach if all
you mean to say is you always need to be בפניו? befanav?
But that's the way the גמרא'ס Gemara's dealing with it right now.
It does not see בורח boreach as a special case. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says, ואיכא דאמרי, ve'ika de'amri, others say, אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב מחזיקין בנכסי בורח. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav
machzikin benichsei boreach. A חזקה chazaka does work. כי אמריתה קמי דשמואל,
Ki amritah kamei deShmuel, now when I said that רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda said it works by נכסי בורח, nichsei boreach, that's what I
learned from רב. Rav. After the way רשב"ם Rashbam says, after רב
Rav died and I went to study by שמואל, Shmuel, I told
this over to שמואל, Shmuel, this idea. Actually, we had that before,
I just didn't explain it. Anyway, after רב Rav died, I went
and told this idea of רב'ס Rav's to שמואל. Shmuel.
אמר לי, amar li, and שמואל Shmuel said back to me, פשיטא,
peshita, of course it works. וכי למחוות בפניו הוא צריך? Vechi limchot
befanav hu tzarich? Of course it works, it's a case of שלא
בפניו shelo befanav and שלא בפניו shelo befanav works.
Now the גמרא Gemara says, ורב מאי קמשמע לן? veRav mai kamashma
lan? Now what is רב Rav meaning to say that it works
by
נכסי בורח? nichsei boreach? דמחאה שלא בפניו הויה מחאה, demecha'ah shelo befanav
havya mecha'ah, that not in the presence works? והא אמר רב חדא
זימנא, Veha amar Rav chada zimna, רב Rav already said it. רב
Rav said that that's פשט peshat of the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma,
יהודה ביהודה Yehuda biYehuda works because you don't have to show up
and be in the person's face. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא
הא קמשמע לן, ela ha kamashma lan, here's what it's telling me.
דאפילו מיחה בפני שנים שאין יכולים לומר לו הויה מחאה. de'afilu michah
bifnei shenayim she'ein yecholim lomar lo havya mecha'ah. Okay, now when he
says נכסי בורח nichsei boreach works, it's what does it mean by
when, how, under what, what will we demand to assume that when
I do a מחאה mecha'ah not in the presence, that the message
will get to the guy? So we're going to raise a whole
list of questions about can we assume in this case the message
will get to the guy, can we assume in this case? So
the first case is, let's say the two people that I testified
are just physically not able to go and to report. Okay, now
this is not what you would think, meaning what I would think
because of בורח, boreach, the reason they're not able to report is
because nobody wants to reveal my location, okay, and therefore, and therefore
it's not going to get. But if that's true, nobody will be
able to report. So the גמרא'ס Gemara's assuming no, we're just talking
about not unique to the idea that I'm a בורח, boreach, but
just the fact that maybe I told it to people that I...
or for whatever reason infirm, okay, not able to travel. I told
it here, I'm hiding out in this, you know, in a hospital
as an orderly in Florida and I'm going to tell it to
the some the people in the in the in the beds that
aren't able to travel, and will that be a good מחאה? mechaah?
Okay, so that's a that's a much more extreme case. It's not
just שלא בפניו, shelo b'fanav, it's telling it to people that they
themselves can't make the trip and tell it to the other person.
Still שלא בפניו. shelo b'fanav. I don't like what?
It's still שלא בפניו. shelo b'fanav. Yeah, so שלא בפניו shelo b'fanav
works. Does this work?
Why? Why wouldn't this work?
Why would why wouldn't it work? Of course it shouldn't work. Why?
Because the two people who know, they're not they're never going to
make the trip.
Why why should שלא בפניו shelo b'fanav if שלא בפניו shelo b'fanav
works anyway
it's because the message will get there. How will the message get
there if they're not making the trip and we don't have telecommunications?
So why does it work?
Why does the message get there? Isn't it important that we just
have a no, oh, no.
No, no, no. It's not enough to know that you announced, because
again well, I keep on switching off who I am, but if
I'm the מחזיק, machzik, okay, then your claim to me is: you
should have held on to your שטר shtar because you knew that
I was protesting your your you know, your holding on to it,
right? So you know, now you're right. You could sort of say,
like, the fact that you protested, that's a I mean, what Eli
is asking is a good point and it deals with two sides
of this. Right? There's two things here. I didn't hold on to
my שטר shtar because I didn't hear a protest. And the other
point is, and the evidence that you sold it to me is
you saw me here and you didn't say anything. If there was
a מחאה שלא בפניו mechaah shelo b'fanav that it didn't get to
me, right? So I, on the one hand, I could say I
had a reason not to be careful with my שטר. shtar. On
the other hand, I can't say your silence proves that I'm the
legitimate owner because it wasn't your silence. So that's actually an excellent
point. Okay, so that maybe so that actually is an excellent point
and therefore you could understand a claim that מחאה שלא בפניו mechaah
shelo b'fanav works even if we're not going to assume the message
will get to me because you no longer have your silence. Okay,
on the other hand, I do want to say that your protesting
in a way that I won't hear about it is not such
a protest. You could also be totally lying and protesting and that
doesn't mean anything if, you know, you can protest all you want
if you assume nobody's going to find out, right? So even to
the degree that the protest the silence proves I own it and
the protest doesn't allow for that, a מחאה שלא בפניו mechaah shelo
b'fanav is not such a good contrary evidence.
Which has also clarified for me what's been bugging me the whole
these סוגיות sugyot is this concept of קלא. kala. Like, people like
think they know all sorts of things. It's ridiculous that it has
legal
force.
But this case, in which you have the מחאה mechaah and it's
by definition impossible it's going to get to the guy there will
be no קול. kol. So in the דף יומי שיעור Daf Yomi
shiur I went to when I was in Israel, the רבי Rebbe
said קול kol has to reach בית דין. Beis Din. That is
to say, that's what he claimed. He said that ultimately it can't
only just be everybody's it got the news got to you it
got
to well, there has to be evidence that there was קול. kol.
But then we'll see about that as we go, because I don't
think there's ever any evidence that there we don't have to know,
as long as I did a right מחאה, mechaah, I don't have
to prove that the קול kol spread, that you heard about it,
that בית דין Beis Din heard about it. Anyway well, we'll see,
well let's take a look and read the גמרא. Gemara. If that
were true, you wouldn't need these any of these discussions. So let's
read the גמרא. Gemara. But I do see that it was an
important clarification point, that to the degree that silence is evidence, that
my lack of reacting is evidence that I sold it, you know,
maybe if I react even if the guy doesn't hear about it,
it undermines that. On the other hand, a reaction that the guy
won't hear about is not such a reaction. So anyway, let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי קמשמע לן מחאה שלא
בפניו הויא מחאה? והאמר רב חדא זימנא! Mai kamashma lan, mechaah shelo
b'fanav havya mechaah? V'ha'amar Rav chada zimna! אלא הא קמשמע לן דאפילו
מיחה בפני שנים שאין יכולים לומר לו הויא מחאה. Ella ha kamashma
lan d'afilu michah bifnei shnayim she'ein yecholim lomar lo havya mechaah. Now
that, I don't know what that has to do with בורח, boreach,
but since רב Rav went out of his way to say that
בורח boreach works, we're trying to understand that he's trying to push
the envelope. And he's trying to say even a real שלא בפניו
shelo b'fanav works, so that would be a case where the guy's
מחאה mechaah will in even in situations where he tells it to
people that aren't going to be traveling back, or aren't even able
to travel back. דאמר רב ענן לדידי מפרשא לי מיניה דמר שמואל,
D'amar Rav Anan l'didi mifirsha li minei d'Mar Shmuel, because I heard
that, you know, שמואל Shmuel said, מיחה בפני שני בני אדם שיכולים
לומר לו הויא מחאה, מיחה בפני שני בני אדם שאין יכולים לומר
לו לא הויא מחאה. Michah bifnei shnei b'nei adam sheyecholim lomar lo
havya mechaah, michah bifnei shnei b'nei adam she'ein yecholim lomar lo lo
havya mechaah. That שמואל Shmuel says no, it only works if you
tell it to people that eventually will be able to travel and
get back. But if you tell it to people that aren't able
to travel and get back, it's not. So therefore שמואל, Shmuel, who
assumes that מחאה שלא בפניו mechaah shelo b'fanav only works in front
of people that are able to travel, said what's the חידוש chiddush
of רב Rav by בורח? boreach? It's a normal מחאה שלא בפניו.
mechaah shelo b'fanav. It's מחאה mechaah to people who are able to
travel because that's the his assumption of when מחאה mechaah works. So
of course it works. And רב Rav says no, I gave that
case because, again, maybe the situation of of בורח boreach is you're
in hiding or whatever, and the people you're telling it to are
people that aren't going to travel. And that's why I wanted to
give that case because I actually think that even in that case
it's going to work and that's my חידוש. chidush. Okay, so ורב
ve'Rav and רב's Rav response to them, why does it work? חברא
חברא אית ליה וחברא דחברא חברא אית ליה. chavra chavra isleh vechavra
dechavra chavra isleh. Your friend is a friend and your friend is
a friend and even if they're not going to travel, they're going
to tell their friends and their friends will tell their friends and
eventually somebody is going to travel and the word is going to
get there. So for whatever reason בורח boreach suggests this idea that
the people I'm telling it to are people who can't travel, but
nevertheless רב Rav is saying that that will be a good מחאה.
macha. Now, by the way, Rabbi Dov to get back to your
point and we're going to see this as the גמרא Gemara continues,
what seems to me extremely clear from all these סוגיות sugyot is
that the original owner does not need to bring any evidence that
the מחזיק mahazik heard of the מחאה. macha. Because if he needs
to bring that evidence, first of all, I don't know how he's
going to find it out, he was far away and how is
he going to be able to find it out and so on,
but then we would not be having these discussions about whether this
stuff works or not. We would just say just okay, maybe I
was מוחה mocheh before people who weren't able to travel. Did it
work or did it not work? Well, if you can bring evidence
the guy heard of the מחאה, macha, then it works. If you
can't bring evidence the guy heard of the מחאה, macha, it doesn't
work. Right? It never seems like we're having that discussion. It seems
like the discussion is all I have to prove is that I
did this מחאה macha with the right parameters and therefore I'm protected.
Right? So therefore and because of the assumption that eventually it will
get to him, but it's clear you don't need evidence that the
word got to him.
Even רב Rav can say there's an assumption, a strong enough assumption
that it'll get.
Not even רב, Rav, רב Rav דוקא davka says that. רב Rav
is the... okay. Now, אמר רבא Amar Rava says רבא, Rava, הלכתא
אין מחזיקין בנכסי בורח. hilchata ein mahzikin benichsei boreach. It doesn't work.
ומחאה שלא בפניו הויא מחאה. umacha shelo befanav havya macha.
But a מחאה macha that's distant works. תרתי? tartei? How could you
say both? Now, one is you could sort of say about the
issue about a case when it's שנים שאין יכולים לומר. shnayim she'ein
yacholim lomar. But the גמרא Gemara makes a better distinction. The גמרא
Gemara says לא קשיא. lo kashya. כאן בורח מחמת ממון כאן בורח
מחמת מרדין. kan boreach machmat mamon kan boreach machmat mardin.
So are you running away because of taxes or you know you
owe the government money or are you running away because of a
charge of murder, מרדין, mardin, murder, murder you might remember that famous
גמרא Gemara what? I murder most foul. Anyway, you might remember the
גמרא Gemara says that now we have the חברייא Chavraya they say
מרדין מרדין mardin mardin and they don't get people off the hook
anyway. So murder. Anyway, so if it's taxes, the assumption is that
the government is not going to chase you. New York will not
run after you to Florida to get your back taxes. So therefore
you're not afraid to make a מחאה macha once you're out of
town and once you're in Florida. Okay, and therefore that's a מחאה
שלא בפניו macha shelo befanav that is meaningful. If however you're running
away because of a charge of murder, then it's you know you
will not make a מחאה שלא בפניו macha shelo befanav because you
don't want to give away your location. And since you don't want
you might wind up hearing the חזקה שלא בפניו hazakah shelo befanav
and essentially works that again that direction works, the message of the
חזקה hazakah is always going to be more powerful and you'll hear
about it but you're not going to be prepared to say anything
because you're not going to give up your location and therefore your
silence doesn't mean anything. Okay. So therefore now of course you always
wonder what happens if there's a whole case. I'm on this land
three years, I say I wasn't careful with my שטר shtar and
you say oh no that didn't work because Charlie was hiding out
because of a charge of murder. I said I had no idea
that there was a charge of murder against Charlie. I had no
idea that he was a בורח. boreach. Nobody ever told me that
so I wasn't careful with my שטר. shtar. Right, so there's like
always these questions here about who knows which information, but
if he's a בורח boreach he'll be
a קול kol to begin with, but let's say there isn't. Let's
say Charlie is legitimately a בורח boreach that nobody knows about and
he's able to prove it three years from now when he comes
back but nobody knows about it. So he has a very legitimate
claim why he did not make a מחאה macha and I have
a very legitimate claim why I assumed that he wasn't bothering and
saying anything because I had no idea about that. So like what
do you do when all of the facts are not known by
all the parties? I really don't know. Charlie, yes, you want to
defend yourself here?
No, he doesn't want to give away his location.
Since strictly we just had this entirely Babylonian Amoraic talk about a
situation of fleeing which is actually fairly common in Rome because Rome
had this system where they would declare people enemies of the state
which allowed anybody to kill them and get their property.
Wow. So you really want to be quiet about where you are.
Yeah, but בורח boreach
comes up in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi as well, but I was going
to ask
whether this was discussed.
It is, it is. Okay, but anyway so we have here now
the idea that מחאה שלא בפניו macha shelo befanav works presumably even
if it's people that themselves are not going to travel because word
will spread and we'll continue to see that. Presumably you do not
need to bring any evidence that the person heard it. You just
have to show that you did your job because that's why we
can have these discussions because You don't need direct evidence that the
person heard it.
And and but if there's a situation where the person is obviously
afraid to say reveal his location, that's a very different, that's a
very different story. Okay, and the pro- question-
what's your question?
So and then it's not a חזקה. chazakah. But the question that
I put on the table is what happens if all the facts
are not known by all the parties? Right? How do you deal
with that case? So now we move on.
היכי דמי מחה?
Heichi dami macha? Let's start, let's get a little further. What is
the words of a
מחה? macha? So מר זוטרא, Mar Zutra, פלניא גזלנא הוא דלא הוי
מחה. Planya gazlana hu delo havye macha. If you'd say, if I
basically say Charlie's a גזלן gazlan and Charlie's on my land, that's
not a מחה macha because Charlie feels Dov is just calling me
names. Okay, what- that's not a legal claim against me. He's just
saying like nasty לשון הרע lashon hara about me, but that doesn't
mean anything. פלניא גזלנא הוא נקיט ליה לארעאי בגזלנותא. Planya gazlana hu
nakit lei le-arai be-gazlanuta. Charlie is a גזלן gazlan and he's on
my land illegitimately. He's stealing my land. ולמחר תבענא ליה לדינא, U-le-machar
tavna lei le-dina, and tomorrow I am going to actually bring a
court case against him. So I am clearly putting Charlie on notice
that I have a legal claim against him. I'm not just סתם
stam calling him names. And he knows that he better protect himself
against that and he'd better hold on to his שטר. shtar. So
in that case הוי מחה. havye macha. There is a מחה. macha.
Now by the way, the- there's a whole discussion in the רשב"ם
Rashbam and תוספות Tosafot of that last phrase ולמחר תבענא ליה לדינא
u-le-machar tavna lei le-dina because we had one phrase against three phrases.
The first phrase "he's a גזלן" gazlan doesn't work. "He's a גזלן
gazlan who's taking my land illegitimately," that's phrase number two. "And tomorrow
I'm going to bring him to court," phrase number three, that does
work. What if you didn't have phrase number three? What if you
just said, "He's a גזלן gazlan on my land illegitimately"? So רשב"ם
Rashbam and תוספות Tosafot both assume that suffices. ולמחר תבענא ליה לדינא
U-le-machar tavna lei le-dina just clarifies why that second clause is important,
because it- it implies that he is taking my property and he-
I am going to defend my claim to my property. But that's
interesting that it had to be the third phrase. The other point
is of course it's לארעאי. le-arai. And this gets back to the
question of an agent. I have to say my property. Okay, so
if you take a look for example...
one minute...
the רשב"ם Rashbam says...
one
minute...
Yeah, if you take a look at the- at the רשב"ם Rashbam
four lines from the top, he says like this. Okay,
לשון אחר שמעתי משמועיה דרבי יעקב בר יעקב ועיקר. Lashon acher shamati
mishmueih de-Rabbi Yaakov bar Yaakov ve-ikar. פלניא גזלנא הוא ואפילו החזיק על
קרקע זה שמחזיק לאו מחה היא. Planya gazlana hu va-afillu hechezik al
karka zeh she-machazik lav macha hi. Charlie's a גזלן gazlan on that
plot of land.
I didn't say לארעאי. le-arai. I didn't say my land. I just
said that plot of land. That's not a מחה. macha. שהרי לא
מיחה מחמת עצמו. She-harei lo micha machmat atzmo. I'm not sort of
defending my own claim, I'm just saying, you know, it's some plot
of land he shouldn't be on. שהרי הוא כמי שאמר פלניא מחזיק
בקרקע של אחרים. She-harei hu ke-mi she-amar Planya machazik be-karka shel acherim.
So if I don't ex- even if it is my land, if
I don't explicitly underscore that, then I am not saying I am
going to be defending my claim to the land. I'm just saying
something bad about Charlie.
Okay. ולפגמו מתכוין, U-le-pigmo mitkavein, I'm just trying to hurt Charlie's reputation.
ולא לערער שהרי אינו מזכיר שהוא שלו. Ve-lo le-arer she-harei eino mazkir
she-hu shelo. You didn't mention it might be yours. But if you
don't mention it's yours, you're not communicating the idea that you are
going to be defending your claim to the land. Okay.
אבל אם פירש דקאכיל לארעאי בגזלנותא, Aval im pirash de-ka-achil le-arai be-gazlanuta,
הרי
מיחה מחמת עצמו, harei micha machmat atzmo, then it's clear that you're
defending your claim. והודיע שהקרקע שלו מחזיק בה בעוולה, Ve-hodia she-ha-karka shelo
machazik bah be-avla,
thank you. והוי מחה. Ve-havye macha. ואף על גב דלא סיים, Ve-af
al gav de-lo siyem, even though you don't end by saying ולמחר
תבענא ליה לדינא, u-le-machar tavna lei le-dina, that's basically what you're communicating.
So basically the assumption is you don't need the third phrase but
you have to imply it.
But what if you say you did-
you skip the second and you just do the first and the
third? Charlie's a גזלן gazlan and tomorrow I'm going to charge- what-
I still think the point is no, because then it's not clear
what you're going to charge him about. If you say Charlie's a
גזלן gazlan and- and I'm going to bring him to דין din
for the land that he's on, for being on that land, then
yes, but if you just- yeah, but then it's already pretty close
to saying the second phrase, you know? The point of the second
phrase is you're making
it- but what if- what if it isn't actually your land?
Maybe you're- oh well that gets to David's point. Oh, Charlie's on
a גזלן gazlan and I'm representing David and saying that David is
going to bring Charlie to a דין din on that land. So
that gets back to- to that question, yeah.
What if- what if he doesn't actually follow through and bring him
to the בית דין? Beit Din? Does that like nullify what he's
even said?
Well if he's not bringing him to the בית דין, Beit Din,
then- then everybody can go home- then- then there's no case. Right?
But if he's tomorrow... oh, tomorrow doesn't mean tomorrow. Eventually. Okay. Tomorrow
means eventually. Okay. Okay. All right. Let's read one more sentence just
to give you a hint. I won't- wouldn't get into this because
this is מוציא דעת, motzi daat, but to give you a hint
to the similar idea about people that... can't travel and again about
how the issue is not whether you can prove the guy heard
but what evidence you can bring about the way you made the
מחאה. macha. So I'll just read you the question for and then
we'll leave you with a cliffhanger. Here's the question we're going to
start with tomorrow.
אמר
רב זביד. Amar Rav Zvid. אמר. Amar. לא תימרו ליה. lo teimru
lei. So there again Eli who is in Florida, he says a
מחאה macha before two people and he says to Charlie and to
Michael. He says to Charlie, Michael, Dov is on my land, he's
eating, he's a גזלן, gazlan, tomorrow I'm going to bring him to
דין, din, okay, but I—don't tell him this. Don't tell him I
made this מחאה. macha. Okay,
now, a, there's two things. A, then we could be really be
afraid that I'm never going to hear it. And b, why would
he say that unless it wasn't a real
מחאה? macha? Like I could say—maybe I don't want him to start
to start—that's a good point, I haven't thought about that—I don't want
him to start collecting ever—false evidence to shore up his case. But
it could also be I legitimately own the land, he's trying to
get it back, and his plan is do a מחאה macha in
a way that I won't find out, wait for me to lose
my שטר shtar and then come with his מחאה. macha. So this
is the question. If he tells them don't tell him, is that
still going to work? Can we still assume a, are we not
going to suspect his reasons for saying that? Okay, and b, can
we still assume that I will get the message? And this is
going to be a series of questions tomorrow of doing a מחאה
macha in a way that raises questions will I get the message.
We've already said even if the people themselves can't travel they'll tell
other people, but what if the מוחה moche is proactively trying to
prevent the message from getting to me? What would be the story?
It's all assuming שלא בפניו, shelo befanav, right. But we...